Lafayette mss., 1572-1939 LMC 2326
Lilly Library
- Manuscripts
  - Chronological
    - Charles Philippe (Charles X), at Fontainebleau - Warrant for household expenses of the dauphin, 1776, November 11; ADS (Box 1, Folder 11)
      "After working out the description, I found that the first son of Louis XVI and Marie Antoinette was not born until 1781. I have not been able to find who was the Dauphin in 1776. Louis XVI became the Dauphin in 1761 at the death of his eldest brother, the Duc du Burgoyne who had been the Dauphin since the death of their father, the then Dauphin, in 1765. Their father was the only son of Louis XIV who outlived this son."
    - Bateman, Nathaniel, English Commander - Letter recapitulating his services under Admiral Sir Charles Saunders, at the taking of Quebec, the reduction of Montreal, etc., 1776, November 13; ADS (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Robert Gordon, Commissary of Provisions to Sir Wm. Howe at "New York or elsewhere in America" - Enclosing invoice of provisions shipped on the "Elizabeth," Capt. Jos. Snowball, for America - advised the Captain to keep company with other Armed Ships, 1776, November 16; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Dr. Philip Turner, at Stanford, CT - Invoice of medicines for use in Hospital - for sick of Continental Line, 1776, November 16; ADS (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Colonel John Montgomery - Pay for services to John Boreman in attending Indian store at Pittsburgh in absence of Mr. Morgan, 1776, December 4; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Agreement written up by Silas Deane and signed by Lafayette - "to serve the United States with all possible zeal, without any pension or particular allowance, reserving to myself the liberty of returning to Europe when my family or my King shall recall me", 1776, December 7; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Also includes typed translation into English and provenance on verso, as well as a letter from librarian Albert C. Bater at the Connecticut Historical Society to Walter P. Gardener about photostat
    - Pierpont Edwards - Receipt for £7.12.0 for flour furnished the Privateer Sloop Montgomery, 1776, December 11; ADS (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - de Vergennes to Duperron - Thanks him for the book on the government of Turkey and discusses the theories of de Montesquieu, 1776, December 11; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Major General James Grant (British) certifies that bearer has taken Oath agreeable to Proclamation of November 30, 1776, 1776, December 12; ADS (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - General Charles Lee, at Basking Ridge, NJ, to General Gates - Telling of the great shortage of supplies, 1776, December 13; Facsimile (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Fragment - Enlistment in the Continental Service under Capt. Anthony Post for twelve months, at Peekskill, 1777, January 21; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Adj. Fowke - Return of Detachments from 10th Continental Virginia Regiment under command of Colonel Edw. Stevens, 1777, April 12; ADS (Box 1, Folder 12)
      "NOTE - This is the Regiment that checked Howe's advance at Brandywine."
    - Mesheck Weare, President, at New Hampshire - "Pursuant to vote of Council and Assembly, pay Major George Gains £1542.16.11 for rum for the State", 1777, April 12; ADS (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - John Williams, at Fishkill - Receipt of £3.4.0 from the Commissioners of Correspondence for apprehending and bringing to Fishkill two prisoners - "William Busby and Enoch Lester", 1777, April 3; ADS (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Thomas McKean, Speaker to Trustee of General Loan Office, Kent Co. - Settlement of account with General Assembly, 1777, February 22; ADS (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - H. Gardner, Treas., W. Cooper and N. Appleton, Committee - Bounty note for £10 payable Dec. 6, 1780 with 6% interest issued by "State of Massachusetts Bay", 1777, February 21; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed, on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - William Carmichael, at Paris, to Arthur Lee at Nantes - French, Spanish and American relations. Lee was on his way to Madrid and Carmichael contrasts the attitudes of the French and Spanish Courts toward the War in America, 1777, February 8; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Josiah Clark to Capt. B. Washburn, at Peekskill - Order for "Money dew him", 1777, January 23; ADS (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - William Henry Drayton, C.J. - Writ of Body attachment for Robert Dick, 1777, January 7; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - General Orders in hand of R.H. Harrison, Washington's Aide de Camp, at Headquarters Morristown, NJ - Giving the parole and countersign - apprehension bounty jumpers who have enlisted again for the bounty money - warning that this will be considered a flagrant and enormous offence and will be punished by execution, 1777, February 6; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 12)
      "General Washington's aide de camp, R. H. Harrison, pens a death order for bounty jumpers --- the words in the lower left corner are possibly countersigns for the day."
    - Major General William Heath, at Headquarters Boston, to Ebenezer Hancock, Deputy Paymaster General to the Forces of the United States of America - "Pay to Samuel Pitts four hundred and sixty six dollars and 2/3 of a dollar in full for a large gelding purchased for His Excellency, General Washington, by his express order", 1777, April 22; ADS (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - St. George Tucker to John Page at Williamsburg - "The devil is to pay in Bermuda" - Tucker had just heard from his brother living there - Neither person or property stand any chance there - refers to the British as "rapacious scoundrels", 1777, April 22; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - D. Britton to Capt. Gideon Foster - "Please to let Jona Williams have 6 lbs of my chocklat and charge my account", 1777, April 24; ADS (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Duchaffault and several other Officers who are about to sail for France - "On Board the Oiseau", 1777, April 26; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lieutenant Colonel Richard Varick, at Ft. George at Tyconderoga, to Colonel Anthony Wayne - General Schuyler is gone to the Convention at Kingston - The Engineers are about to sound the depth of Lake George, 1777, March 5; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lieutenant Colonel Richard Varick, at Albany, to General Anthony Wayne at Tyconderoga - Congratulations on Wayne's promotion, General Patterson is here and says that M.G. Sullivan is to come to this Department with a whole train of Eastern Officers which has nipped in the bud the pleasing information that Major General St. Clair, yourself, and General de Haas were to come - "God grant that the Eastern information may be groundless or woe be to us" - "How will you and his Excellency General Carleton cast up accounts together should he be mad enough to come down and take Tic. from you", 1777, April 2; Photostat 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - William Carmichael, American Agent in Paris, to Col. Tench Tilghman, an aide de camp to General Washington - Letter of introduction carried to America by Lafayette, 1777, March 17; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Includes transcription with contextual information about letter
    - Samuel Freeman, at Boston, to Elbridge Gerry - Refers to teh recruiting - "Near 7000 men are needed - would to God our Army was completed" - Charlestown, offended at the delay are again asking for compensation for their losses - "I congratulate you on the arrival at Portsmouth of a ship from France", 1777, March 24; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 12)
      "NOTE - This was the Ampitrite, one of the three ships outfitted by Beumarchais and it brought a party of French officers as volunteers."
    - Colonel Francis Barber - Warrant for payment for wheat, 1777, March 26; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - James Winthrop, Richard Derby, Dr. Samuel Holton, Benjamin Austin and eleven other Councilmen, at Boston - Order to pay £1200 bounty to men mustered into the Continental Army, 1777, April 2; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - A. Brasher and Abr. Ten Broeck, Pt., at Kingston, N.Y. - Pay for services in attending the N.Y. Convention and Committee of Safety, 1777, May 14; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - John Lansing, Jr., secretary to Major General Schuyler, at Philadelphia, to Board of War, State of PA - Respecting a prisoner charged with attempting to "alienate the minds of the Indians", 1777, May 21; ADS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Robert Troup, at Albany - his receipt for $100 received from Jonathan Trumbull for pay as Aide de Camp to Major General Gates, 1777, June 3; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - John McKinly, President to Casar Rodney, Trustee of Loan Office of Kent Co., at Wilmington - Pay warrant to Captain Thomas Skillington for the expenses of the "flying camp Battalion", 1777, June 17; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - James Young certifies that Peter Browne of Kingsington has taken his "Affirmation of Allegiance and Fidelity" in Philadelphia, 1777, June 24; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed, on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 13)
      "Browne was evidently a Quaker as the word "Oath" is ruled out."
      Printed by John Dunlap
    - Phillip Schuyler (Gen'l), at Stillwater, to the "Militia Officers and Committee of Berkshire" - "An event (advance of Burgoyne's Army) so alarming has not yet happened since the Contest begun and yet by strenuous exertions we may prevent the enemy from penetrating." Entreats them to at once march all their men to Albany - "Time is too precious to apply to the President of Massachusetts." This is a marked copy but it carries "sent me by Major Sedgwick - teste, Oliver Wolcott," and on the reverse is endorsed "Intelligence from the Northern Army", 1777, July 7; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Col. Wm. R. Lee and Major General William Heath, at Cambridge - Muster roll of the Regiment of Foot under Col. Lee, 1777, July 13; ADS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Daniel of St. Thomas Jenifer - Receipt, 1777, July 26; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - John Paul Jones, at Portsmouth, to Robert Morris - Outlines his plans to carry the Naval War into foreign waters and so draw off the British from the American Coast, 1777, July 28; Photostat 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Le Bien Aime," at Brest - Concerning 4 dozen lignum lanterns, the panes of which are to be repaired - signed by de Bourgainville, 1777, August 5; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes typed translation into English (with correction on separate sheet)
      "Louis Antoine de Bougainville, 1729-1811 - served in Canada in 1758 under Montcalm - again in 1759 at the capture of Quebec. In 1778 he served in the Revolution commanding the "Auguste" and managed to save his ship in the engagement on April 12th, when Rodney defeated de Grasse."
    - Lafayette to John Hancock, President of Continental Congress - The young Frenchman, then not quite twenty years of age, beautifully expresse his sentiments toward the new Nation and his gratitude for the Commission of Major General he has received, 1777, August 13; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - General Washignton, at Neshamony Bridge, to Benjamin Harrison on the subject of Lafayette's appointment, 1777, August 19; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Benjamin Harrison's reply to General Washington, 1777, August 20; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Brooks and Odionne, Coms., at Exeter - "Received of Caleb Moody - 3 £ in counterfeit bills of N.H. State", 1777, August 28; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Major John Ashley, Jr., at Sheffield, to Major General Lincoln at Bennington, VT - Warns him that because the farmers have their grain to get into the ground he thinks the men of his command will not turn out, 1777, September 7; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Itemized receipt for construction materials, 1777, September 10; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Adj. General Thomas - Pass to Ft. Montgomery, 1777, September 24; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
      "NOTE - It was issued two weeks before the Fort was taken by the British."
    - Note listing death of Captain Banks, Commodore of H.M.S. Renown, 1777, September 12; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Verso includes note about author's examination of the "Renown Books"
    - Robert Long certifies that State of Maryland owes Clement Brooks £290 for use of his seven horse team used in bringing cannon from Indian Landing to Elk Ridge Landing (after retreat at Brandywine), 1777, September 26; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - La Chere d'Eon, at Versailles, to M. Fagonde - "The metamorphosis I have been forced to make has not succeeded quite so well in my case at that of Ovid. There are so many openings in this new uniform that the North Wind, regardless of that of the Court has swept through my chimney from bottom to top and has terribly ravaged my chest. Happily there has not been a fire there for forty-nine years otherwise the Water Tower of Versailles would have hardly been enough to put out the conflagration.", 1777, August 6; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 13)
      "NOTE - d'Eon had been called home from London by Louis XVI and ordered to dress in women's clothes."
    - J. Halsey, Recruiting Officer, 3rd Brigade - Giving authority to Isaiah Cook to take up all deserters, 1777, October 7; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Marie Adelaide, Victoire and Sophie (daughters of Louis XV) - All three Princesses sign an accounting for expenses, 1777, October 3-7; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lafayette to General Washington - writes about his own affairs "with all the confidence of a son, of a friend, as you favoured me with those two so precious titles." He asks Washington's advice about a command "because I was diffident of my being able to conduct it without knowing the character of the men", 1777, October 14; Photostat 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes typewritten note and heading on scrapbook page
    - Joseph Trumbull (Commissary General), at Hartford, to Eldbridge Gerry at York, PA (where he was attending Congress) - Explaining his difficulties, rising prices, lack of commissary stores - "No one is planning to purchase next year's supplies." Washing his hands of the responsibility, he says "let the curses of the people light on those who deserve them", 1777, October 15; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Major General William Heath and Lieutenant John Burgoyne - The American General requests the Commanders of the British Ships cruising on the Coast of Massachusetts Bay "to permit the Schooner Polley to proceed to Eastern part of State and return with a Load of Wood for the use of the Troops of Lieutenant General Burgoyne" - warns that if the Polley is detained the British soldiers will be the sufferers. Lieutenant General Burgoyne, in his own hand - "concurs in the above pass, Major General Heath having engaged his faith that it shall not be employed for any other purpose", 1777, November 14; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Statement of enrollment of Captain Adam Wheeler's Company, 1777, November 14; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - General Washington to Congress - Suggesting that Lafayette be given a separate command, 1777, November 26; Photostat 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lafayette replies to General Washington's request for his choice of Winter quarters, 1777, December 1; Photostat 3 p. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lafayette to Major du Bouchet at General Gates' Headquarters - He regrets that ill health compels Bouchet to return home, 1777, December 1; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Josiah Bartlett (S. of D.I.) - Order of Committee of Safety, NH for £30, 1777, December 12; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - George Read, Vice President of the Delaware State, to Trustee of Loan Office Kent Co. - Settlement of account with General Assembly, 1777, December 20; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Itemized receipt for ammunition used at Bennington and Fort Schuyler, 1777; ADS (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Aaron Day, Lieutenant, 3rd Jersey Regiment, at Valley Forge - "I do certify that Major Joseph Morris of the 1st Jersey Regiment is dead: that he died 3rd of this instant and I saw him buried the 4th", 1777, January 15; ADS (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Captain Richard Dowling of the 20th Regiment (British), at Cambridge - Pleads that he be allowed to go home to England because of deaths in his family, 1777, January 26; ADS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      "NOTE - He was a prisoner of war interned at Cambridge under the Saratoga Convention."
    - Allen McLane, 1746-1829, to "Sir", 1778, January 29; ADS (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lafayette to the President of Congress - A long letter on his plans for the Canadian enterprise and requesting definite instructions on certain matters, 1778, January 31; Photostat 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lafayette to Captain Hubley at Camp - concerning supplies, 1778, January; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - La Perouse (the famous navigator) - Signed while he was an officer of d'Estaing's Fleet, 1778, February 8; ADS (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Major General Benjamin Lincoln, at Albany, to Major General Conway - After telling of the difficulties of the situation he gives it as his opinion that these are "insurmountable objections to prosecuting the intended expedition into Canada", 1778, February 16; ADS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      "NOTE - The letter was written the day before Lafayette reached Albany."
    - Henry Gardner, Treas. State of Mass. Bay - Bond for £53 payable Jan. 1, 1780 in Spanish milled dollars, at six shillings each, 1778, February 19; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed, on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Governor Clinton of New York writes to Lafayette - "It gives one real concern to learn that the preparations made for the expedition which you was to have commanded, falls so far short of what you had reason to expect", 1778, February 26; Photostat 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      "The military Governor of New York writes about the ill-fated Canadian Expedition"
    - Arthur St. Clair (Major General), at Barnstable - Promissory note for £302, 1778, February 26; ADS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Louis Jean Marie de Bourbon, Duc de Pentheivre - Also signed by de Courdray (who was drowned in America during the American Revolution) - Official appointment, 1778, March 4; Printed document, with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - General W. Skinner to Governor Caswell of North Carolina - Complains of profiteering - the price of course shoes rise from 16/ to 26/ occasioned by some Maryland Merchants engaging all that was to be had - "I can't collect a shilling of taxes", 1778, March 5; ADS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lafayette certifies that Lieut. Joseph Lewis has taken the Oath of Allegiance, 1778, March 14; Facsimile on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Paul Turquand, at York Town, PA, to the Continental Congress - Prays relief because certain Bills of Exchange, certified by the President of South Carolina, have been dishonored, 1778, March 9; ADS (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lafayette to Congress - "When General Gates left this place he ordered that as a reward to the troops who had bravely contributed to his success, a gill of rum should be given to each soldier in Albany and also to the workmen, that I dare not alter till I will have directions from Congress or the Board of War, but beg leave to observe that I have had complaints from the Commissary about the scarcity of rum." "There has been a court martial for desertion which I didn't approve of, but as among other men you have found sentence of death, I beg from Congress to be empowered to relieve the man", 1778, March 20; Photostat 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Admiral de Grasse, also possibly by La Perouse (his navigator), on board l'Orient - On equipment, etc., 1778, March 27; ADS (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Rev. Isaac Rysdyk, at Hackensack, NJ, to Rev. Dirk Romein - Church matters, 1778, March 29; ADS (Box 1, Folder 14)
      "The Reformed Dutch Church at Hackensack was organized in 1686, and its congregation has always used the one site for its Church buildings. The first was built in 1696, the second in 1736 and the present building in 1791. Rev. Dirk Romein was a Hackensack native, graduated at Princeton in 1765 and after his pastorate at the Hackensack Church was called to Schenectady in 1785, where he died in 1804. Rev. Warmoldus Kuypers was one of the Schrallenbergh Congregation. Garritt Leydekker was the Pastor of the English Neighborhood and Solomon Fraeligh of the Millstone and Neshanick Churches. The letter is in the old style Dutch, which was used for all Church records up to 1799."
    - Justice Thomas Bee, endorsed by Edw. Rutledge, at Charles Town, SC - Writ to Sheriff to attach bodies of Alex. Rose and John Torrans in action of trespass, 1778, April 7; Printed document, with autograph fill-ins, signed on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Lafayette answers General Washington's request for his views on three points, namely - "Attacking New York, attacking Philadelphia or staying in a fortified camp till the enemy will go out, and laying a plan of conduct for that case", 1778, April 25; Photostat 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Lafayette to Robert Morris - On money matters, 1778, April 26; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Admiral Count de Guichen, at Brest - Orders for the Marine Guards, 1778, April 27; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Vicomte Lomange to his father - Saying he was first considered an adventurer but that his good conduct, of which Lafayette will tell his father, has changed everything. He hopes to be a colonel of the regiment commanded by de la Rouarie. He suggests that letters to him should be addressed to the American Camp, not to the Camp of the Rebels, 1778, April 30; ADS 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes typed description on scrapbook page, with bookseller's description pasted on verso
    - Louis XVI and other Officials on "Garde de Mon Tresor-Royal" Certificate, 1778, May 4; Printed document, with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 1, Folder 15)
      "NOTE - It was the custom for a Minister to sign the King's name, but under some circumstances the King signed his own name in addition. This paper carries both signatures."
    - F. Eichelberger and Wm. Scott, Justices of the Peace, at Manchester Twship, PA - Conrad Snyder would not serve in the War and a substitute was secured at cost of £38.15.0 - Snyder's refusal to pay resulted in the Levy, 1778, May 13; Printed document, with autograph fill-ins (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - General Washington to Henry Laurens - describing the Lafayette episode at Barren Hill, 1778, May 24; Photostat (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Lafayette to President of Continental Congress - He proposes that, in order to accelerate a declaration of War by France on England, there shall be an expedition against the British West Indies, under Continental colors, the French to provide a Man of War, soldiers and hard money, the spoils of any conquest to be divided among the Americans and the French., 1778, May 25; Photostat 6 p. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      "NOTE - Lafayette had learned in April of the Treaty of Alliance but evidently did not know what France proposed in the way of an active participation in the War."